I told a whole story about what it's
like to be a pilot and what it's like to
do that and what it's like to lead men
into that over and over and over again.
And I just felt like that perspective as
a historian, as a veteran. Um, and and
really like as a woman, there's not a
lot of women that do this too. I could
tell those stories. And I feel like I
learned because I have friends who can't
tell their stories that I will lean into
the discomfort of talking about myself
and tell their stories because their
stories deserve to be told. And I will
do that because I'm the one left behind.
And I I'm honored to be left behind and
tell their stories.
Hi, I'm John Kuryaku and welcome back to
Deep Focus. You know, it's not often
that we have someone who is a bonafide
hero uh on the show, but we have such a
person today. And not only is she a
hero, at least in my estimation, not
only does she have a wonderful story to
tell about wartime and what it was like
going into war in the immediate
aftermath of 9/11,
but she has a fascinating story about
her postmilitary career. Jennifer Benny
was a helicopter pilot. She had a great
career, an important career, and a
career in which she accomplished a great
many things. We're going to talk about
that. But then after her military
career, she decided to focus on history.
The same kind of history that I like.
So, I'm not going to tell her story. I'm
going to let her tell her story.
Jennifer, welcome to the show. It's good
to see you.
>> Thank you for having me. It's good to
see you, too.
>> So, I want to talk first about your
decision to join the military. Do you
have a military tradition in your
family, or was this something you just
decided was the right thing to do?
My parents are both uh mil Air Force uh
they're Air Force veterans. They're Air
Force Security Police. I was born at in
Fateville, North Carolina. My parents
were stationed at Pope, but I was born
at Fort Bragg because the Army Hospital
was the only hospital there. And uh and
it's interesting because my mom was one
of the first female security police in
in the Air Force. and she was the
actually the first one in Aviato, Italy.
And uh she met my dad. My mom's from
Queens, New York, uh raised in Jackson
Heights, went to PS69 Bryant High
School. My dad is a small town
Pennsylvania boy from the outskirts of
Pittsburgh. A big cornfed, you know, he
his claim to fame was his high school
football team. Won the entire state
championship for Pennsylvania.
>> What What town was that? It's Houston,
Pennsylvania. It's south of Pittsburgh.
I actually went to the same high school
because when my father got out of the
military, we moved back to be close to
family. I graduated with 69 people.
That's how big this high school is. And
they won the entire state championship
for Pennsylvania. So that was his big
claim. But he's a big guy, 63, 240, big
guy, a lineman. And so he meets my
mother in in Italy. Doesn't think women
should be in the military. Thinks that
they make everyone weaker. that he they
have to watch out for the women. My mom
stood up. Queens, New York said, I you
if you have a problem with that, then
you shouldn't be here because I'm doing
my job, you need to do yours, not focus
on me. And they got married three months
later.
So those are my parents, right? And so
when my mom was in they from Avano, they
got stationed at uh at Pope and my mom
was thinking of getting out of the
military. She had just had she had me,
she had my brother 18 months later and a
general was walking around. my mother
again, kind of poster child for the
women in the in the military at the
time. And so much so that she was
testing out the new maternity uniforms.
They didn't even have them at the time
for the military. And a general had
asked her, "What could I do?" Because
she was like, "I'm thinking of getting
out. I just had kids." And he goes,
"What could I do to make you stay in the
military?" And she goes, "If I had
orders to Hawaii, I'd stay in." So three
months later, my mom had orders to
Bellow's Air Force Base in Hawaii, which
is the recreational base. If you know
anything about it, it's all cabins.
Obama would stay there. They have a
presidential cabin there. Uh and so my
father also got orders to Bellows. Uh
Magnum PI would film on Bellows while
while uh it was there because the the
public couldn't come on. My mom was a
personal bodyguard for Tom Celich,
right? So I'm a little kid not knowing
anything, right? And I'm like, "Oh, Tom,
you know, I thought his name was Fabric.
I mean, a Magnum." And he would carry me
around. But it's this time we moved, we
got orders after that to Wyoming and I
saw the Thunderbirds for the first time
and I said, "I'm going to do that. I'm
going to fly jets." And if you know
anything about my maiden name was
Mitchell. So if you know anything about
Top Gun, right, I I was the real
Lieutenant Mitchell, Naval Aviator
Lieutenant Mitchell. So my my I was
never married in the military. So my
name the entire time was Mitchell. And
so Jets, Jets, Jets, Jets. I'm going to
go Air Force. So my father gets out of
the military in Wyoming. We move back to
Pittsburgh. I go for the Navy
scholarship. I go for the air the
military scholarship to Penn State. And
I went to the Air Force first. And the
Air Force said, "You have to major in
math. We love you. We think you're
great, but you have to major in math."
And I was like, uh, I'm not sure if I
want math. One floor up was the Navy.
And I said, what what can you guys
offer? And they said, we love you. We
would love for you to be a pilot. Uh,
major what you want. And I said, I'm
going to go Navy. So that's why I
completely changed to Navy. Still jets
though. Still wanted to fly jets. So
between your junior and senior year of
ROC, I had a full scholarship to Penn
State ROC. Uh, they send you to an
aircraft carrier to see what you would
want to do in the in the military.
Right. I got sent to the Eisenhower in
the Mediterranean 1998.
>> Eisenhower. It's a city on the water.
>> Yes. And it was I flew into Nice. Like
it's my first time going to Europe. I
flew into Nice. I met the ship in in
Cans, right? I saw where the Can's film
festival was. I'm like, "This is
amazing." and met the ship and they
attached me to the helicopter squadron
because they had a female pilot and they
wanted me to interact with the female
pilot. I'm like helicopters. I didn't
even know the Navy had helicopters. I
thought that was Army. And on an
aircraft carrier, the helicopter job is
pretty much one of the most boring jobs.
You're the first to launch, the last to
land. You fly what they call starboard
D. So it's a starboard, looks like a D.
You fly in a circle on the starboard
side of the ship and you're waiting for
someone to crash, right? You're the
first. That's why they're first one
launched so they can do all their air
ops and then you're the last one to
land. So when all the air ops are done,
you land and you're just you're airborne
in case something happens. Right.
>> I didn't know they did that. That's the
first time I've ever heard that.
>> Yes. And so I was like, helicopters,
whatever. I want to fly in the F-14. So
I had gotten all of my qualifications
before I left. And now I I will cry out
this. I'm a swimmer and I'm not just a
swimmer. I'm a butterflyer. So, I have
very strong arms, strong shoulders. So,
I had to do all the parachute stuff
where they drag you through the pool and
you have to unleash yourself. I had to
do the dunkers and I got all the
qualifications to if I was to get a hop
in a jet. I was ready to do that. I made
sure I had all of it before I went out
on this midship and cruise. This is
1998.
No women in any of these jud squadrons,
right? women had just been allowed into
combat three years earlier, but it
wasn't like I tell people it was like it
was all these women waiting, right? They
they allowed it, but there weren't women
doing it. There were a couple women who
had qualified, but they weren't deployed
or anything like that. And so I walk
into and this is the Jolly Rogers, so
they're the skull and the crossbones,
right? And uh they they took no
midshipman. Usually midshipman get
attached to a squadron. I was attached
to the Hilo Squadron. I think there was
S3s that took another midshipman. Uh I
walk into this F-14 ready room. I sit
right in the front row. And if you any
know anything about a ready room on an
aircraft carrier, the front row is CO,
exo, opso, admin. It's all the high
ranking officers. I sit right in the
front row as the commanding officer is
speaking at the podium and he looks at
me in very colorful language and tells
me to get out of his ready room. and I
say, "No, I'm not leaving." I'm like,
"This is my dream and I want to fly." I
tell people a lot of times, "My smart
mouth either gets me something pretty
amazing or in a lot of trouble." And
this was a moment, one of those defining
moments in my career. And he looked at
me and he goes in another color, "Where
do you go to school?" And I said, "Sir,
I go to Penn State." And he goes, "Big
10, you're flying." Because he went to
Indiana in the Big 10.
And that moment he did that, every guy
in that squadron treated me fantastic. I
was allowed to go into the the Jolly
Rogers anytime I wanted. They gave me
their patches. I flew in an F-14 off a
carrier, sat in the back seat like
goose. We the co flew at the same time
in his jet, played the Indiana fight
song, and I was I was like, "This is it.
I'm going to fly jets." We caught the
trap on the way in. It was amazing,
right? I I it was one of the greatest
moments in my aviation career. Like I
just it was amazing. Everything I
wanted. I knew this was what I wanted to
do. And like I said, they were he was
great with me. They were all great.
Three days later, I'm in the Hilo
because again, I could choose what
flights I wanted to fly every day on in
the helicopter because I'm attached to
that squadron. And I just sit in the
back with the rescue swimmers, right?
And I'll be like, I'll go on this flight
today. Get off the carrier. Something
fun to do. We're in Starboard D. I'm
back with the rescue swimmers. There's
two of them back there. We're kind of
just goofing around and we hear aircraft
in the water. Like you hear the thing
that you're like, "Oh my gosh." And I'm
My eyes got so big. We all And they
start throwing their gear on. Two F-14s
had hit each other.
>> Oh my god.
>> They had clipped wings just like um they
were trying to dog fight, which we don't
really practice as much anymore because
there's not really a country that can
fly as well as us. It's not an ally. So
they clipped wings. They got too close.
The pilot I had flown with actually was
one of them. He made it back to the
carrier. The other one went into the
Mediterranean.
And just like in Top Gun, the pilot
died. He hit his head on the canopy, got
wrapped up in the parachute and drowned.
We rescued the NFO naval flight officer
like Goose who sat in the back. When you
sit on an ejection seat, you wear these
shin straps that pull your legs up under
the seat because you're basically
sitting on a rocket, right? Well, one of
them had failed and he basically saw his
leg shoot up right in by his face. So,
he had broken his leg basically and um
was barely attached and so when they got
him into the hilo, he's screaming. The
rescue swimmer splinting it and wrapping
it and we're going back to the carrier
and then they eventually will fly him to
Turkey to save his leg. I help with the
stretcher, right? Because they get them
and and I'm again, I'm a midshipman. I
know nothing, but I'm wearing a flight
suit. I'm in the back of this hilo. I'm
watching everything. And I just help
with the stretcher as we get to the
carrier. And he looks up at me and he
said, "When I heard the rotors coming, I
knew I was going to be okay." And that's
when I said, "I'm going to be a
helicopter pilot."
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Right.
>> What year was that?
>> This was 1998.
And I'm still friends with that no. I'm
friends with him on LinkedIn.
Um the pilot I flew with has
subsequently he he went on to be
commanding officer flew F-14s but he
subsequently has died of cancer and he's
at Arlington. I visit his grave and tell
his story. His call sign was Rhino. But
uh after that I went to flight school.
So this is I graduate from Penn State
1999.
You graduate in uniform. You're
commissioned the day before you
graduate. So when my parents come to my
graduation, they can at least pick me
out of the 10,000 people because I'm in
my uh uniform instead of capp and gown.
And then I go to flight school. And
flight school again, being a swimmer was
such a benefit for me. I beat everybody
in the pool. We do a mile swim in full
flight gear. I beat everyone. Like
everyone, men, women, didn't matter. I
was first out of the pool. So much so
that the guys who ran the training tank
gave me the best time. They're like,
"Mitchell, this is the best time. Can
you beat it?" I'm like, "I can beat it.
Get everyone out of my way because you
have to swim around everybody, right?"
And they're like, "Oh, we can't do
that." I'm like, "I can't. I'm trying to
maneuver between everyone who's slower,
but I can beat that time." Now, I didn't
beat it because again, there was like 20
of us in the pool, but um but I beat
everybody. And I made a point. I could
do pull-ups. I could lift a guy on my
shoulders. I could do I mean, I'm not a
small girl. I'm 5'7. And so, it kind of
helps because when you're going through
aviation uh physiology, you have to get
measured everywhere, right? Shoulder to
hip, hip to knee, uh shoulder to the end
of your hands because you got to fit in
a cockpit that was built for men, right?
And so being a bigger woman helped and
being able to do those things helped.
And I think having a mother who proved
herself in in a a male-dominated field,
she told me, "Just do the things. Just
do all the things and let them see you
do the things, Jen, and that'll be
enough." And it was true. I trained with
all these guys. I could throw a guy on
my shoulders. And I never heard anything
about
>> So you can't do it.
>> You weren't intimidated by this at all.
>> No. And I tell people, they ask me,
"Where does that confidence come from?"
Yeah. And I think it's because I had a
6'4, 240 lb father who 100% believed in
me.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. People always say, "You're a
woman in the military. Do you have daddy
issues?" And I always laugh. I'm like,
"If you meet a father who loved and
supported me and I never had to worry
about, you know, having a male figure in
my life, uh, yeah, I had daddy issues."
Like I had a father who was a he became
a high school football coach after that.
He was also a uh you know in the law
enforcement and he 100% believed in me.
He was like you can do it Jen just go
out there and do it. I have 100% faith
that you can you can achieve this. So
because I had the support of both my
parents I didn't care what anyone else
thought right I didn't and I was I was
making the grades I was getting the
scholarships I that had that great
experience on the Eisenhower. I felt
very reinforced
by my confidence that I could do this.
But I tell people flight school, right?
I graduated 99, started flight school in
2000, the beginning of 2000. It's it's
hard. I had never flown before,
>> right? No private pilots license.
>> You started from scratch. So, when you
were when you were 17, 18 years old, you
weren't out at the local municipal
airport in the in the Cessna 172 taking
the the flight lessons.
>> No, because as much as like I would have
loved to have done that, my parents were
bluecollar workers, right? I I could not
have afforded school without the Navy. I
I had good grades, but not good enough
to get a full academic scholarship. I
had good grades to get a full Navy
scholarship, you know, and um and so I I
had to work all my summers just to
afford the basics when I got back to
school. And so uh I never had a chance
for any anything sub, you know, extra
before I went to flight school. I had
just watched Top Gun a million times.
But I tell people, your first flight,
they show you everything. Your second
flight, you take off by yourself. your
third flight, you land by yourself. You
can't do that. You're out.
>> We're talking helicopters here. I I
actually got my pilot
>> fix wings.
>> Fixing. Okay. I got my pilot's license
in in 2000, the summer of 2000.
Um only because
I I worked in a in a group of five guys
in in a CIA station overseas. And in the
course of conversation one day, they all
mentioned that they all had their pilots
licenses. And I said, 'Oh, please.' I
said, 'If you dopes can get pilot's
licenses, I can, too. And we laughed.
And I mentioned to my ex-wife, um, hey,
everybody in the branch has a pilot's
license. I think I'm going to I'm going
to give it a try. She said, what? You're
too stupid to get a pilot's license. You
have to you have to be good at math and
and calculus and stuff like that.
So, I went home on RNR and my dad and I
were in the car driving to Walmart and
there was I I'm also from Western
Pennsylvania, Newcastle, Pennsylvania,
which is just north of Pittsburgh.
>> So, and and we also had a killer
football team.
>> Uh still do. In fact, we're anyway we're
number one right now, but that's a
different issue. So, um, I was taking a
shortcut to the Walmart and it was past
the local airport and they had a banner
out front and it said, "Learn to fly
here." So, I said, "Dad, let me pull
over for a minute. I just want to go in
and ask them a couple of questions." So,
I parked the car. I run in. I said, "How
much does it cost and how long does it
take?" And he said, "Um, it's $5,000
flat and if you're serious, you can do
it in six weeks." And so I learned to
fly in six weeks. Now landing is hard.
Taking off is easy. Flying the plane,
the plane wants to stay in the air. It
flies itself. Landing is hard. And what
I'm going to ask you about in a second
is
>> flying a plane is one thing. Flying a
helicopter is an entirely different
animal.
>> So you're training in a fixed wing
aircraft.
>> And then what? So, everyone who goes to
flight school trains in fixed wing. Um,
and again, it's to weed you out.
>> And, and what do you what kind of fixed
wing are you training on?
>> A T34 mentor. You probably have seen
them. There's they're on the flight deck
of the Intrepid. Uh, they're painted
orange and white. Like, stay away from
me, right? Students are in here. Uh,
it's it's a it's a turborop. It's a
pretty powerful aircraft because I'll do
my I'll do all my aerobatics in that
aircraft. I learned how to fly form in
that aircraft. I do a cross country in
that aircraft. That's what you all
everyone does this in primary flight
school and uh it's a lot of testing
beforehand like you said it's a lot of
like aerodynamics and thermodynamics and
weather engines. They throw a lot of
testing quickly at you in eight weeks
and you fail to you're out and 80% is
passing. So that's how they first weed
you out and then it's a lot of physical
fitness tests, right? And that's that's
even before you fly. A lot of physical
fitness tests and eyes, all those things
for pilots, right? Color blindness,
eyes, all those things that could also
disqualify you. And then you start to
fly fix wing, which I like again, first
flight they show you. Second flight you
take off, third flight you land. And you
brief these flights for an hour before
you even get in the cockpit. You have to
talk through every procedure. You have
to have studied them. And I always would
get like the hardest guys, like the
people who had the reputation of being
very difficult. And I remember being
like, "Okay, got to do it, Jen. You got
to do it." Right? So, I would just put
my head down and study and learn and get
in there and just give it my best. And I
think they want to see that, right? They
want They're trying to weed out people
who are not confident in themselves
because you want a confident pilot,
right? You want a pilot who's like, "I
can do that. I'll figure it out. We'll
get we'll get in. We'll get out. We'll
we'll get them. We'll save them." And
so, I think they're looking for that
foundation of you as a as even as a
learner. And so, yeah. And I loved it. I
learned it quickly, right? And I just I
loved being in the sky. And I tell
people my first solo was my 13th flight
is your first solo. And like you said,
we fly every day. And if you I think you
become a better pilot flying every day.
It's a lot of studying.
>> It's a lot of work. Yes. Right.
>> But it's just like driving. If you drive
every day, you're going to be better.
And same thing with flying. It's a like
you're studying your butt off. But that
13th that 13th flight, you're solo. You
take off. You go to another field. You
do five touchand goes and they watch you
and they grade you. And then you have
like an hour to go back to the, you
know, Pensacola, your original field.
And uh I climbed up in close to the
clouds and I could see my shadow on the
cloud and I could see just me in the
cockpit like no instructor and I put my
hand on the windscreen and I had never
felt such a sense of accomplishment in
my life.
>> Like I did it. I did this from nothing.
>> I from nothing. my dream. I brought it
all the way through to fruition. I can
do this, right? And that's just my first
solo, you know. From there, you learn
arerobatics, which is so much fun. You
know, spins and dives and rolls, and
then you do two solos doing that on your
own in the cockpit. So, you're pulling
G's and you're making sure you don't
pass out because you're flying solo. Uh,
I loved flying form. You learn how to
tuck in, right? So when you see the Blue
Angels, when you see the Thunderbirds,
how they're tucked into each other,
looking at a sight picture. I tell
people, you never take your eyes off the
other aircraft, you're constantly
looking at them. You don't look at your
cockpit at all. You're making little
movements to keep that sight picture
perfect. And the only person navigating
is the lead, the one who's looking
outside. You're just with them. So you
don't even know when you're rolling.
You're just so tucked into that sight
picture that you're just going. you
don't even realize that what you're
doing aerobatics wise and so uh I loved
form and then from there you graduate
primary intermediate is your cross
country and then you go to advanced and
advanced is rotary wing and yes learning
to hover is divine
because it is hovering is little micro
movements they call it I'm stirring the
soup right because to hover to hold a
hover is these little micro movements to
keep you in a nice balanced hover. And
uh you learn all these things with
helicopters because you have to learn
how to auto rotate. Auto rotation can
save your life. It's the only way to
save the aircraft from an engine
failure. You practice auto rotation
every time you fly. And so it was a
different animal, but I loved it. I
loved you're low, you're slow, you do a
lot of land navigation and uh I knew my
job in the Navy would be a lot more
saving lives than taking lives. And so,
but so this is all happening
in 2000 and I just finished flight
school the beginning of September 2001
and again my mom's from New York. I'm
done with flight school. It's September
4th. I walk into my commanding officer's
office and I said I I we had talked
before. They had never had a female
pilot at all in Japan. I wanted to be
that female pilot in Japan. My CEO said,
"If you're first, Jen, if you're first,
I'll make sure you're the first female
pilot in Japan." I walk into his office
September 4th. I said, "How's it
looking?" He goes, "You're first. You're
going to Japan." I'm like, "Awesome.
September 11th happens, right? My
parents are coming in for my winging
September 14th, my mom calls me. I'm
sleeping in because I'm done with flight
school.
Uh I pick up the phone. My mom's from
New York, right? And she's like, "Turn
on the television." And I saw we we the
first plane had hit, right? And that's
when I was like, "What? What's going on?
Did they was that a mistake? Were they
was it was it out of fuel? Was it the
engine failure? and they crashed in and
then we saw the second plane hit on I
watched it on TV with my mother and I
said, "Mom, I got to go." I knew in that
moment it was an attack. I knew it. And
um my commanding officer shut down the
base, right? All the bases were shut
down. Called us all, told us to meet him
at a Waffle House off base. My whole
winging class, I'm winging with about 20
people
and we meet at the Waffle House. and
he's like, "Okay, uh, bases have been
shut down." This is when we knew
everything. We already the Pentagon had
been attacked. And so, um, Shanksville,
the crash had happened in Shanksville.
And so, we all knew something was going
on. And he's like, "You're anyone who's
coming to your winging, we need all
copies of documentation. The cars will
be searched. You only get one vehicle
across. Uh, so who's ever coming to your
winging, we need to all that
documentation now. Orders are being
pulled." And he looked at me and he
goes, "Jen, they need you in San Diego."
And I said, "Yes, sir." He goes, "That's
where you're going." I said, "Okay." So,
I didn't even question it, right? I
didn't even question what helicopter I
was flying, what was needed. I I tell
people, I joined the Navy to see the
world, to get college paid for, to fly,
and all of a sudden now I'm going to be
fighting, right, fighting a war. Now, I
knew that could be a possibility, but it
was not what I had specifically joined
up for, but I was ready to do my job.
And uh so September 14th happens, my
parents come to my winging. It's
fantastic. And then I'm supposed to ship
out to San Diego to start Seir School.
So, we'll talk about SER school
waterboarding, right?
>> Um I'm set to start Seir School in
October 2001. I go up to ground zero
about two weeks after it happened and uh
I take my cousin Marissa because again
we're from New York so my mom's sister
is my godmother who I'm and they live in
New Jersey. So, we get up there about
midnight. We walked from Penn Station.
It's all quiet, right? And we get up
there and that's when they have the big
spotlights and there's still all the
missing posters. And I walk up to a cop
and I said, "Where can I get a New York
PD patch?" And he goes, "All the stores
are closed right now." And I said,
"Okay." I said, "I'm a Navy pilot. I'm
about to ship out to San Diego. I would
like to fly with a New York PD patch on
my arm. I'm allowed. You know, you have
to wear the flag on your one uh
shoulder, but you can fly anything you
want on your other arm. And he goes,
"You're a pilot." I said, "Yes." And he
ripped it off his coat.
>> Wow.
>> And he handed it to me. I still have it.
>> Wow. Yeah.
>> I Yeah. I flew with it every mission.
>> Wow.
>> So, uh, from there I went to San Diego
to SEIR school. And I always tell
people, so SEIR is the best and worst
training I got in the military, right? I
learned
>> explain to our viewers what what SEIR
is.
>> So it's survival, evasion, rescue, and
escape. It's how you would interact as a
prisoner of war or if you were shot down
and the possibility of you being
captured as a prisoner of war. And you
learn what your rights are under the
Geneva Convention, which I didn't know,
right? You learn, they teach you how to
be a prisoner of war because in Vietnam,
men were captured and tortured and they
felt so ashamed of themselves because of
what they divulged that they didn't want
to come home, right? And they were so
ashamed to come home that they don't
they they felt that they didn't prepare
them for that. And so SEIR is to prepare
you for this. And so you learn uh what
your rights are. You learn how to be
interrogated. You learn what kind of
things they will do to you, the
psychological warfare, and then they
take you in the field to kind of test
the that knowledge that you learned,
right? And
we all kind of think of it as prisoner
of war training. And we all know we're
going to get our butts kicked, right?
That's kind of what we
There's no easy way to get through Seir,
you're going to be tortured is what it
comes down to.
>> And when I went through, they
waterboarded and they made it very clear
in Seir school. If you were
waterboarded, you died. If you're
waterboarded, it means that you didn't
do what we taught you and you didn't
because they teach you like
you have two types and I'm sure you know
all this, John. You have two types of
information. You have critical
information 24hour what your mission was
and you have long-term information what
your job is and what you know and
they're trying to get both of that
information from you and your job is to
act like you have it. You can't get it
because you're so traumatized, right? So
you're still an asset to them. They
won't kill you because you have this
information they want. You just can't
access it because it just everything is
happening right now. So your job is to
kind of act like I know it. Give them a
little tidbit of something so they know
she definitely or he knows what they're
talking about, but I just can't get to
it. So what they teach you is you can't
say nothing. You can't say, "I'm not
telling you anything. I know nothing."
You get your butt kicked and you still
know nothing. Because they're just going
to kill you because they're not going to
get anything from you. And then you
can't give them everything because they
like they got everything from them. Then
they're just going to kill you. So your
job is to keep alive. Keep alive with
honor. And you probably know all this,
right? And so they teach you when they
put the gun to your head. This is your
utmost. This is when you're at your
utmost. You're about to break. You're
about to die. Give them a piece of
information. Let them know something.
And so when that happened to me, right,
I get my butt kicked. I tell people I
got punched in the face and my ear
started ringing and the person was
yelling and I'm like, "Wow, it really is
like the movies." They're like, "Wow,
your ear just rings." And you don't hear
anything coming out of their mouth. I
was just so shocked. I was just like,
"Wow, that really does happen. It sounds
like a a you know, a artillery or
something went off in your ear. It's so
loud with the ringing if you get hit
that no matter if the person's
screaming, you can't make out any word
they're saying." So that was me. It was
mostly shock factor, right? And uh but
she put the gun to my head. She put the
9 millimeter to my head and asked me
what kind of aircraft I was on. They
teach you a whole scenario before you
go. And I told her, I think it was a and
I told her the number and then she took
the gun away and put it away. And that's
when I knew this is what they're
teaching you. But if you didn't say that
and she pulls the trigger, you get
waterboarded. And I could hear people
being waterboarded. I could hear it. And
I said, "I'm not mm- I learned." And so
I never got waterboarded, but I could
hear those guys. And they were
screaming. They were coughing. And I'm
like, "Did anyone pay attention in
class?" That's what I felt like when I
was like, "Did anyone pay attention in
class?" They said, "If you get
waterboarded, you didn't make it."
Right? Like that's not a good thing. So
I knew I learned how to do this game.
Now, I tell people I was very lucky
because I went through SER school with
two other women and they are very uh
unpy. They if a guy's not answering
questions, they pull a woman out and
they start to hit her and make the guy
watch them hit her. And there was one
girl who was smaller than me and cried a
lot. And I hate to say it, they pulled
her out from almost everything. And so I
got lucky because you get hit so much. I
tell people, your face is just numb by
the end. Like you're just like, "Yep,
okay, another hit." I had bruises up and
down my chest. I think you talked about
how they slam you against the wall,
right? Like they just slam my head
against the wall and they interrogate
you with the big light and they teach
you all this stuff in Seir School. Like
they're going to interrogate you with
the big light and you know and they're
going to ask you questions. They ask me
like very pinpointed questions like
what's my designator and I'm like how do
they know that word? And they asked me
what my security clearance was. And
thank God,
>> John, I had just I had just upped it.
Like I was in between. So I didn't know
what I had. That's right.
>> And so I kept saying, "I don't know."
Because I really didn't know.
>> And in the end when I got debriefed, the
guy was like, "You were so good about
not giving us your clearance." And I'm
like, "Well, because I honestly didn't
know what it
>> Yeah.
>> But I It's a lot. It's They
>> It's tough. It's traumatic.
>> It's traumatic, but I always tell people
it's the best. It's the worst training
because I really did get my butt kicked
and I lost a lot of weight, but I
learned a lot. And I learned how to take
it. I learned um how I would react. I
learned how other people were going to
react, right? And how will you ever know
unless you get into it? But being a
woman, um, I learned too flying in the
Middle East that more than likely if I'm
captured, I will probably starve to
death. They probably won't even waste a
bullet on me to kill me because they
don't think I'm worth even
interrogating. They will put me in a
cell and not feed me and I probably just
starve to death and die. That's what I
learned. So I learned my greatest chance
of survival is another woman of another
Middle Eastern woman because they see
westernized women as hope. And so if I
flew with a religious symbol, they could
relate to that and my greatest chance
would they would be helping me escape.
They would, you know, sympathize with
me, empathize with me. They would
release me and help me escape. That
would be my greatest chance of survival.
So, I flew with a cross um all the time.
And I learned like even after my first
deployment, I tell people as a blonde, I
got my hair pulled all the time. They
just don't see blondes. And I don't I
tell people they I did they didn't do it
to be I knew they weren't doing it to be
mean. They just couldn't believe I was
really a blonde. Right.
>> Right. And they were just like, "Is she
really a blonde?" And they would call me
Brook Shields. And I would be like,
"Broo Shields, call me like Jennifer
Aniston or something." I'm like,
but uh but I learned a lot about,
you know, the the different dynamics of
where you're flying over and you know,
we learn about blood chits and things
like that. Like, let me ask you about
that if I could interrupt you for a
moment.
>> Sure. Um, each time I went to
Afghanistan after 911,
you you fly into usually I'd fly into
Kabell, sometimes directly into Bram,
but then to go elsewhere around the
country, you have to take a helicopter
for the most part.
>> And when you're landing, you have to
evade or you have to be prepared to
evade rocket attacks. Mhm.
>> And so when we're landing, we're doing
this corkcrew, a very tight corkcrew
like circle. I I laugh now in retrospect
because to me, you know, the the side
doors of the of the helicopter open, so
you're looking out, you're spinning in
this tight corkcrew. People around me
were throwing up
and it didn't bother my stomach for some
reason. And I just thought it was really
cool. It was explained to me why that
was so important because people really
do fire stinger missiles at you or
rocket propelled grenades at you.
>> That's our biggest threat.
>> Tell us about about training for that
and then actually doing it.
>> So I was in Iraq and I um and I was we
did so much. I tell people I felt like I
was in a Tom Clansancy
>> Oh yeah. movie.
>> Yes. Right. In real
>> I did all the things. I flying night
vision every night. Seal teams in and
out. Right. Cover ground air cover. And
I I have a a busted blood vessel in my
eye right now. I only ever got that in
Iraq on NVGs because of the eye strain,
right? And I'm like, "Oh my gosh, am I
getting stressed again?" But it's it's
funny 20 years later. But uh no, so like
you said, our biggest threat as a
helicopter because we're low and slow
are the the self-propelled missiles uh
man pads, right? The ones they can fly
off of their arm off their shoulders.
There's two types of missiles, heat
seekers and radar seekers. And so I can
tell right away in my helicopter what
I'm being lit up by, but I only have a
moment, a moment to react. So you
practice it every time. If it is a heat
seeker, you're going to turn right into
where it's coming from because the
coldest part of my helicopter is the
nose. I'm gonna turn and dive and just
so they can't see me. So even if they
fire it, it's going to go high. It's not
going to it's not going to hit the heat
of an of the hilo. They also love if you
can get the sun behind you. So turn in,
go low. If it's nighttime, oh, just get
low and turn into it because again, the
coldest part is the nose of the
helicopter. If it's radar seeking, your
job, you have basically like a radar
screen. Think of it. Your job is to fill
that screen with metal as quick as you
can. That's why you're cork screwing,
right? Fill that. So, you juke, right?
You juke and you try to fill that screen
as quick as you can with metal. So, it
can't pick out where you actually are.
Doesn't have the time to coordinate on
you, right? You're not staying in one
position and you're not keeping that
relative motion. And so, that is why you
corkcrew. You're filling up this um
screen with as much of metal, you know,
radar detection as you can. Uh your most
vulnerable time is landing because
you're coming low and slow. You don't
have time to auto rotate if something's
going to happen. So that's why we would
do those types of landings. Plus, we
used to learn in flight school to hover
then land. And in the sand of the Middle
East, we would have issues what they
call brown out. a helicopter would push
the sand up into the screen. You
couldn't see and helicopters were
crashing. That happened a lot in the
beginning. And so we learned right away,
you just plant it. You come in and you
hit the deck, right? And so we would
practice that every time. And I'll be
honest with you, John, I flew with so
many people and again, I loved
helicopters. I just had a great feel for
it. I flew with so many people be like,
"That is the best approach I've ever
seen, Mitchell." And that's how I knew.
I'm like, I am really good at this. And
I I you know,
in the military, I tell people all the
time, especially when I got into my
squadron, my call sign was Yoko because
I broke up the band, right? First woman.
Um
I was told by a lot of people to keep my
mouth shut, right? But people wanted to
hear from me and they would be keep your
mouth shut, Mitchell. like and I would
so I didn't talk a lot about when I was
going through
you know the deployments we didn't take
photographs of ourselves we didn't post
pictures of ourselves we didn't talk
about our jobs we did our jobs right I
was studying my butt off I'm still
learning I'm still testing I'm still
learning parts of the helicopter if
there's an emergency how can I save it
right like I'm still I'm so every day
working out, making sure I'm staying
fit. Uh I always thought if the if I
crash and I can run, the Navy Seals are
going to be held up by my pace. So, how
fast can I run? So, I always stayed in
great shape for that. Like, I really
thought a lot about what I was doing and
and how I was doing it. Plus, I learned
early on being one of the few women that
I'm also setting the modeling to the
other women and to my men what this
looks like, right? And I would hear from
my men like, you know, we didn't like
women in the military, Mitchell, but we
like you. And I learned early on, I
really don't care what your opinion is
of women in the military.
>> It's liberating to not care what other
people,
>> but I'm not going to be your example,
but why women shouldn't be. That's how I
kind of felt about it. like I don't care
what your opinion is, but you'll never
use me as any example for why women
shouldn't be. And that's kind of how I
saw it.
>> Um I I'm gonna I'm going to brag for a
moment. Um I have a lifelong love of
cemeteries.
I love the the piece and I love the
architecture. But what I love the most
is the fact that everybody has a story.
Everybody, everybody has a life
worth living. And so,
one of the great joys I have in life is
just wandering around cemeteries,
looking up random people to see what
their story is. This is something that
you've done. I've got a book coming out
in the next u well the next month or so
um on the historic cemeteries of
Washington DC. But you like cemeteries,
too. And you Well, you know what? I'm
gonna let you tell your story. Tell us
about what you're working on right now
and how it connects your love of
cemeteries and your experience in the
military.
>> So,
after my two deployments, right, my
initial commitment in the military is
up. I saw those moms kissing their kids
goodbye for deployment. I wanted to be a
mom and I didn't want to do that. So, I
got out after my initial commitment and
I got married to an active duty Navy
officer. He's still active duty now. And
I had children, right? Because I'm later
in life. So, I had three kids right
away. And then I decided, what do I want
to do with my life? And I, especially in
Iraq, John, I was like, what is the
story here? Right? Like, you get out
there and you're like, what's the
history here? There's history here. And
we don't learn that going out, right? We
don't know what's the big beef and
what's the fight and I want to know more
about that about America, right? I want
to know why do historians say this is
what happened? How do they quantify
this? How do you primary source this?
And so I used my GI Bill to get a
master's degree of history and I I
learned how historians do that. And I
learned everyone has a story and I
learned that the best places to tell a
story is is not only where we start but
where we end.
Right. And even Arlington is so much of
a story of America. Just that space in
DC is so much a story of America that I
wanted to tell those stories. And so I
started Walk with History, which is
takes you on location. I like that it's
on location so you can step into the
steps of history giants and be there.
And so I started with Arlington's movie
stars because I found that nobody really
knew Marino O'Hara was buried at
Arlington.
>> That's right. And James Coburn and
people like that.
>> And no one had put her on YouTube. No
one had connected the dots. And I said,
I'm going to do this because I'm a big
John Wayne fan. I'm going to tell Marino
Harris story. So we went there. I went
to her grave, told her story. Why is she
in Arlington? Right. And then the
Arlington story came out and then I
wanted to do to the Tuskegee Airmen
there and tell their story. I wanted to
do the women of Arlington. I wanted to
do the Band of Brothers there. And no
one had done that, right? Everyone loves
the Band of Brothers, but no one and
then when I did Masters of the Air, I
did that before this book even before
the show came out. When I did Egan, who
is the main guy, he's buried with his
wife, who was a wasp, and no one had put
that together. He married another female
pilot and I was. And so as a historian,
those are the stories that are like the
real stories of these people. And with
the military background, I wore my
flight jacket and I talked about her
being a Wasp and him being a pilot. So I
felt like I could tell more of the
connection that these two had. Why are
they at Arlington? And what was at, you
know, the mighty ETH and what what were
these men doing at the time? and what
kind of heroism that looked like to fly
daylight bombing missions during World
War II. So, I told a whole story about
what it's like to be a pilot and what
it's like to do that and what it's like
to lead men into that over and over and
over again. And I just felt like that
perspective as a historian, as a
veteran, um, and and really like as a
woman, there's not a lot of women that
do this too, I could tell those stories.
And I feel like I learned because I have
friends who can't tell their stories
that I will lean into the discomfort of
talking about myself
and tell their stories because their
stories deserve to be told. And I will
do that because I'm the one left behind
and I I'm honored to be left behind and
tell their stories.
>> Well, this this has book written all
over it. Uh no pun intended. Um you give
tours, walking tours, lectures, any
plans for a book, any plans to maybe
pitch something in Hollywood?
>> So, it's so funny you say that. Um, I'm
am writing a book right now about the
Wasps of World War II, right?
>> Very much like a League of Their Own.
It's kind of a historical fiction
because it's not quite what happened,
but I take bits of all these women from
these different classes from all over
America and how they're so different and
how they at first are very much against
each other because you see that in
flight school too with other women.
Women against women can be very
powerful.
uh and they learn that they're
sabotaging themselves and that this this
whole program won't pass unless they
pass together and they have to come
together as a group to become this first
class of female pilots. The Wasps flew
every military aircraft that was
produced during World War II. as they
were coming off the assembly lines as
fast as they were coming, these female
pilots fied them all around America and
it opened up a thousand men to go fight
uh thousand pilots to go fight in World
War II because they stayed home and
fedied all these aircraft and I don't
think people know so much about their
story. These women pilots who did it,
they flew the B29, they flew every
aircraft and so it's it's their story.
It's a basically these women who
overcome their differences to prove that
women can do this in military flight
training and they become that first
winging class that's going to fly these
aircraft. And I it's really much like
it's a historical fiction, but I think
it's kind of a story America needs right
now that we're stronger together than a
than apart and then if we have a common
goal that we really there's nothing we
can't do.
>> Amen to that. So tell us how people can
read more, learn more about what you're
doing, connect with you. How do they do
that?
>> So Walk with History has new videos
every Wednesday, Walking Wednesday. And
and like you said, John, I like to tell
stories, veteran stories. I'm actually
doing a story right now on Michael
Murphy. Michael Murphy was the only Penn
Stater to receive the Medal of Honor.
I'm a Penn Stater. Uh, I'm class of 99.
He was 98. You would know Michael Murphy
from Lone Survivor. He is the Navy Seal
OIC officer in charge of Operation Red
Wings. And Michael Murphy will expose
himself to enemy fire to make the radio
call to save his men and ultimately will
be what saves um the the lone survivor
to save uh his life. But he is fatally
wounded in that process. He does die on
uh June 28th, 2005. And then he's
posumously awarded the Medal of Honor.
Penn State does have a uh a park
dedicated to him, but I feel like more
people need to know his story. This man
who went to Penn State, who decided to
become a Navy Seal, who did all of this,
it's awarded the Medal of Honor. I think
more people need to know his name and
what he did. So again, people who can't
tell their story, I want to tell his
story. Um, our lives paralleled each
other. I tell people all the time like I
was 99, he was 98. He went to Pensacola
for OCS. He was going to go to law
school, then decided to go to OCS and
become a SEAL. I was in Pensacola for
flight school. He went to San Diego for
Buds. He graduates in October 2001. I'm
in San Diego for SEIR school, right? He
gets stationed in San Diego. I get
stationed in San Diego.
I don't know if we ever met. I don't
ever remember meeting him. It seems to
me the very classic uh courage under
fire. Remember when he sees her in the
helicopter and he remembers seeing her?
I feel like Murphy and I may have seen
each other at some point, but I didn't
learn about him till after he died.
>> Well,
Jennifer Benny, thank you so much for
joining us. This was I wish we had
another hour to carry on this
conversation because we we just barely
scratched the surface. But thanks very
much for being with us.
>> Yes. And like I said, Walk with History
YouTube Wednesdays. We have the Talk
with History podcast, which will explain
how to do those things. How do you go to
Arlington and visit Marine O'Hara? How
do you go to Arlington and visit uh
Gunnery Sergeant Irmy? Listen to the
Talk with History podcast as you drive
there. I tell you where to park. I tell
you where to go. I tell you where to
walk. That those come out every Monday.
You can find me at Facebook, Instagram,
and uh I interact with people all the
time. So please let me know what history
is important to you, what you want to
see, what you want to know about. But it
was such an honor to talk with you,
John.
>> Thank you very much for that.
>> I'm very much inspired by your life as
well and the courage you have shown.
>> Thank you very much for that. I
appreciate it very very deeply. Thank
you. And I also want to ask ladies and
gentlemen, if you like the show, please
like, subscribe, share. That's what
keeps us going. we get to have great
great guests like Jen. Thanks again for
being with us.
>> Thank you.